בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is צדי א', Tzadi Aleph,
91.
We are in the middle of a debate, we sort of got
into it as a digression of a digression a bit, but we're
in the middle of a debate of רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva and
who was it,
who was it, שמעון התימני Shimon HaTeimani about whether the בית דין
Beis Din has to directly see the murder weapon. And they learned
this from the פסוק pasuk וכי יכה איש את רעהו באבן או
באגרוף, ve-chi yakkeh ish et re'ehu be-even o be-egrof, that somebody is
smitten with a stone or a fist. So שמעון התימני Shimon HaTeimani
says, well, the same way בית דין Beis Din could directly inspect
the guy's fist, they have to be able to directly inspect the
murder weapon. Now, by the way, the פסוק pasuk itself is really
talking not about murder but about inflicting injury,
but the debate of רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva and שמעון התימני Shimon
HaTeimani focuses on murder, and does the בית דין Beis Din have
to directly see the murder weapon. שמעון התימני Shimon HaTeimani says yes,
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says you're never going to be able to
see all the circumstances about how the act of murder was committed,
and therefore you have to trust the עדים. edim. You trust the
עדים edim about everything else, you rely on them, so the בית
דין Beis Din themselves does not have to see it. Fine. The
גמרא Gemara then introduced this strange ברייתא, braisa, which really again in
some ways belongs in the first half of בבא קמא, Bava Kamma,
that if a שור shor both murdered and killed and caused injury,
so if it's a שור תם, shor tam, then you would first
do the then, you know, you're not going to get the guy
who was injured isn't going to get paid because it's going to
be a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, it's not going to be worth
anything, so you just do the judgment of the שור הנסקל shor
haniskal and the guy who got injured is just not going to
collect because his only ability to collect is from the body of
the שור shor itself. But if it's a מועד mu'ad where the
guy's going to pay cash for the injury, it says even there
it says it's important to first do the judgment of it as
for payment and then do the judgment for a שור הנסקל. shor
haniskal. And if you reverse the order, the guy can't be paid.
So the גמרא Gemara says why can't the guy be paid? Right?
I mean, okay, you reverse the order. It's a שור הנסקל. shor
haniskal. Big deal. You still have to pay cash for the injury.
So here's how it tied back in. רבא Rava says he found
the rabbis of the בית מדרש Beis Medrash and they were saying,
"Ah, this is שמעון התימני." Shimon HaTeimani. And according to שמעון התימני,
Shimon HaTeimani, the same way you have to see the murder weapon,
the בית דין, Beis Din, not just witnesses, the בית דין Beis
Din has to see the injury weapon and not just for a
person who inflicts injury, but even for a שור shor who inflicts
injury. So you got to bring the שור shor directly into בית
דין Beis Din for them to look at the שור shor and
determine could this שור shor really under normal circumstances have inflicted the
damage that it did. We don't have a question that it did
inflict the damage, but if it was not something to be expected,
maybe that would be a reason to be exempt from payment. The
גמרא's Gemara going to get back to that. I know it's a
מועד. mu'ad. I know, we'll get back to that. Okay. Well, but
nevertheless, under these circumstances it's a good point. Anyway, that's how they
explain it. And since the בית דין Beis Din has to see
the murder weapon, well, if the שור shor ox is already made
a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, you can't say, "Oh, don't stone it
yet, we need to hold it off so the בית דין Beis
Din can look at it for this next case of this injury
case," not just injury done, only murder weapon, the injury weapon, let's,
we gotta hold, we gotta not stone it yet, we gotta wait
another week because we're dealing with this other case. So that wouldn't
be fair, wouldn't be fair to the poor שור. shor. And here
it's so interesting that the same way the גמרא Gemara in the
past had said
that the process of making something a שור הנסקל shor haniskal is
similar to the process of judging a person liable for an act
of murder, here actually it says it's also true about postponing the
execution. That the same way that's considered to be anguish and affliction
for somebody who has been ruled to be liable, you know, to
get capital punishment, it would be affliction to the שור shor to
have to postpone its execution. Like it's so ironic, bizarre, I mean,
how does the שור shor even know that it's this order has
been issued? Anyway, that's one explanation. So the reason you have to
do it in this order is once it's a שור הנסקל shor
haniskal you'll have to stone it, you can't postpone stoning it, and
then בית דין Beis Din won't be able to look directly at
the weapon as it were that committed the injury. That was the
first explanation given. Yes, Rabbi Domba?
Yeah, I think in American law you can bring a capital case
and then you can sue for damages.
Well yeah, that's the O.J. Simpson. That's when they lost the capital
case. That's true. We're not saying you can't.
In other words you can never do that?
No, no, no. This is specifically about the שור הנסקל shor haniskal
and because and you can't and it depends about the order, it's
only for the reason said. Okay, I mean how that would play
out in other cases and קים ליה, kim lei, but this is
specifically about a שור הנסקל shor haniskal and the order being dealt
with
here, confined to that.
Yeah, I mean now it is true if it's a case of
a human being who commits murder, that's something we've discussed before, there's
no civil suit for a case of murder. Okay. So anyway the
גמרא Gemara says ואמינא להו אנא, v'amina le'hu ana, three lines from
the
top on צדי א' עמוד א'. Tzadi Aleph amud Aleph. So רבא
Rava said I said back to those rabbis in the בית מדרש,
Beis Medrash, אפילו תימא רבי עקיבא, afilu teima Rebbi Akiva, I have
a way of explaining this even according to רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
that you don't, the בית דין Beis Din doesn't have to see
the murder weapon. So if the
בית דין Beis Din doesn't have to see it, why can you...
And because the owner ran away, you can't have a court case
without the owner being present. You can't judge somebody not in their
presence. Of course the point is, if that's the problem, who cares
what order you're judging the ox, if the problem is that the
owner isn't here? אי ברח, i barach, if the owner ran away,
כי לא
דנוה לדיני נפשות, ki lo danuhu le-dinei nefashos,
even if they hadn't done the, you know, murder trial, the שור
נסקל shor nishkal trial first, היכי דנינן ליה לדיני ממונות, heichi daninan
leh le-dinei mamonos, how could you judge the ox for, you know,
for paying for the injury, בלא בעלים, belo be'alim, without the owner's
presence? So, you know, what does that mean the owner ran away?
Then that has nothing to do with the order! If the owner
ran away, you can't have the court case. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, fine, דקבלו סהדי וברח. de-kibbelu sahadi u-varach. No, fine. Okay.
First
we did accept witnesses that this ox was a שור נסקל, shor
nishkal, and then the owner ran away. Okay, and now we can't
judge it for being a, you know, for what do you call
it, for, you know, for doing the injury. Of course the question
still is, it has nothing to do with order. It just has
to do with the guy, the issue that the owner isn't here.
So the גמרא Gemara says סוף סוף מהיכא משתלם? sof sof me-heicha
mishtalem? So where would you, where would the owners be like... So
here, so what the גמרא Gemara is saying here is, is that
the problem now is not that you cannot have the court case
not in the owner's presence. You, you know, you accepted the witnesses
already. So it's basically these hearing of the witnesses that have to
be in the owner's presence, and that took place. But here's the
problem. The problem is that we don't have any access to the
owner's assets. Okay, because we don't have any access to the owner's
assets, so presumably the witnesses came and testified that they saw this
ox both murder and, you know, create injury. So we have to
decide now, okay, we have testimony that we can now use for
two court cases. Which one are we going to deal with first?
And the, the problem is that there's no assets to collect from
except this ox. The ox is the one thing that's left here
that, you know, otherwise you wouldn't be able to have a judgment
of a שור נסקל. shor nishkal. Otherwise the owner ran away, absconded
with all of his assets. So here's the problem. Problem is if
we judge דיני קנסות dinei knasos first, okay, I mean we judge
the injury first, so then maybe we can pay the guy off
by using the ox. So let's judge דיני קנסות, dinei knasos, the
נזק, nezek, pay the injured party off by giving him the ox,
and then we're going to judge שור נסקל shor nishkal and make
it a שור נסקל. shor nishkal. The only question is, how am
I going to benefit from giving this ox if you're going to
turn it into a שור נסקל? shor nishkal? So the answer is,
ah, what we'll do is we'll let you use the ox long
enough so, you know, in your field and plowing so that you
can get paid off for the cost of the injury, and maybe
it'll take a year, and then we'll deal with the שור נסקל
shor nishkal case a year from then.
Okay, I can see understanding like a killing animal.
I understand, well, that's a good, that's a pretty good question. I
don't, that's a very good question.
Wait, wait, but he can use it in the field, sell it,
keep that cash?
No, no, because I don't think so. Because that, well, he could
sort of sell the right to use it in the field, but
otherwise it would be like a מקח טעות, mekach taus, selling it
to somebody and you know it's going to be turned into a
שור נסקל. shor nishkal. But anyway, but he could sell somebody else
the right to use it. But afterwards, anyway, Michael asks the next
one question, you know, when exactly you have an obligation to kill
an animal, you know, not because of שור נסקל, shor nishkal, just
because this is a hazard, like the גמרא Gemara spoke about a
כלב רע. kelev ra. So the ראשונים Rishonim discuss, like, what are
the scenarios, like, and sometimes maybe you can do a good enough
שמירה shmira and if you're responsible enough we don't make you, we
don't make you, you know, kill the animal, but it's a really
good question. Anyway, let me finish the point. So, so if we
do the order right, we have the, we accepted the witnesses. Now
we have to decide which order are we going to do the
court case. If we do the order right, we can pay off
this guy for the injury, let him use the ox until he's
got paid back, and then we'll have the שור נסקל shor nishkal
case. But if we do it in the other order, then it'll
become שור נסקל, shor nishkal, and then we can't have the guy
use it. Why can't we have the guy use it after it's
שור נסקל? shor nishkal? Not because it's אסור בהנאה, assur be-hana'ah, because
it's not אסור בהנאה assur be-hana'ah until it's dead, you might remember
that. But because once it's a שור נסקל, shor nishkal, same problem,
he can't spend time using it plowing because it's not fair to
the poor ox that you're postponing the execution. Okay? But that's the
scenario, Rosa. The scenario is not the שמעון התימני Shimon HaTimni that
the בית דין beis din has to see the weapon. The scenario
is is that the party has to be paid from using the
ox to plow, and therefore we have to do it in the
right order or we're going to be postponing the execution of the
ox. I want to just read that inside the גמרא Gemara and
then you can ask your questions. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay,
סוף סוף מהיכא משתלם מרדיא? sof sof me-heicha mishtalem meradya? Where would
he be paid off? From the plowing. You see? And that's why
you have to do it in this order, because he can be
paid off, and not in the other order, where then you would
be postponing the execution of the ox. Okay? אי הכי, ei hachi,
but the גמרא Gemara says one minute, if you can pay a
guy from the plowing of an animal, you know, even if the
animal is going to be... executed, as long as you haven't made
it a שור הנסקל shor haniskal yet, תם, tam, נידייני דיני ממונות
ברישא. nidaynei dinei mamonot be-reisha. So why by תם? tam? By תם
tam we said it doesn't matter, either way the guy isn't going
to get paid, you know, it doesn't matter what order you do
it. But it does matter what order you do it. Same solution.
Have the guy even though this will be a שור הנסקל shor
haniskal and a תם tam can only be paid מגופו, mi-gufo, but
now have the guy use the גופו gufo of the animal to
plow and get paid back and then you'll make it a שור
הנסקל. shor haniskal. That works for תם tam also. You're getting that
benefit from the body of the ox. So do it in that
order. So the גמרא Gemara says נידייני דיני ממונות ברישא ונישתלם מירדיא
והדר נידייני דיני נפשות, nidaynei dinei mamonot be-reisha ve-nishtalem mi-radya ve-hadar nidaynei
dinei nefashot, and then we'll make it into a שור הנסקל. shor
haniskal. So אמר רב מרי בריה דרב כהנא זאת אומרת, amar Rav
Mari berei de-Rav Kahana zot omeret, this teaches you רדיא אליה דמארי
הוא. radya alya de-mari hu. The benefit of plowing is not considered
the body of the ox. That's considered like other assets of the
owner. Okay, so when we say an ox, you know, the injury
for damage of a שור תם shor tam is from the body
of the ox, then that means from actually how much the ox
itself sells for. And that ox itself is going to become a
שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. So you can't say I have a right
to use the ox to get paid back before you make it
a שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. No. That's not getting paid from the
body of the ox. That's getting paid from some other benefit that
the owner has. And therefore it doesn't work in a שור תם
shor tam case, but it works in a שור המועד shor hamu'ad
case. Yes, Michael?
I was kind of under the impression that the בית דין Beit
Din has to take the cases as they came up, but they
couldn't necessarily pick.
Yeah, but apparently the witnesses came into both at the same time.
But does it make a difference like who brought the... I mean,
you know, some had to come first. This guy got killed, this
guy is coming.
This other guy got injured, this guy's family...
well, but there's also a question about, like you know, equity. You
know, I mean it's an interesting question in general. If they were
really two completely unrelated cases, let's say you brought one case and
you brought witnesses, and another person brought another case and brought witnesses,
and we figured out for some reason that... No, no, no. Not
about the same ox. Some unrelated cases. I mean, at least the
very body, you know, the sort of substance of the cases was
unrelated, but somehow if we were to judge this case first, that
would cause... you know, that would mean you would never get, you
know, you would never be able to collect for your case. Would
we use that to factor in and say therefore we're going to
give priority to yours, because that'll get everybody justice? I don't know,
that's an interesting question. But here anyway, it's not separate cases. Right?
It's all about the same ox, and it sounds like the witnesses
testified about both things at the same moment. So to some degree,
you know, they're both being presented to us at effectively the same
time. So we're going to choose the way that's going to lead
to the greatest justice.
All right? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, yes.
I have two questions. One, you said if צער tza'ar doesn't apply
to an ox, right? In other words, he can't be sued for
צער. tza'ar. Right. And the other is, isn't it, it sounds somewhat
like a fiction this idea of like if it has to be
killed once it's judged, that it should be killed immediately so it
doesn't...
Right, I don't think we really believe that the ox is going
to anguish, but we're just being very formalistic about the same way
you would treat a human being, you're going to treat the ox.
I mean, I think what it does is to underscore that we're
not trivializing, you know, we're looking at this as like real, like
murder. You know, one way to think about this by the way
is because the תורה Torah is so radical, you know, for its
time, in saying... because the law of Hammurabi was your ox kills
somebody, kills somebody's child, your child gets killed. You know? So the
תורה Torah is being very radical, and
the תורה, Torah, the פשט pshat of the פסוקים pesukim say that
basically if it did it three times you should be killed, you
are killed, executed, but you can pay a כופר. kofer. But it
sounds like the simple reading of the תורה, Torah, if you don't
have the money to pay a כופר kofer we would execute. The
rabbis read that you're never killed, you just... you know, there's just
a כופר kofer payment. So because what we've done is now... but
you know, we're so much... so that's like a radical shift and
somebody could say that's so unfair. His ox killed, you know, someone
and all that happens is you just kill the ox? Like you
know, that's not real justice being done. So it could be that
if we make the process of turning it into a שור הנסקל
shor haniskal exactly like the process of, you know, holding up somebody
for an act of murder, you know, that maybe creates... it does
somewhat to balance that, you know, creates some greater sense of justice
being served. But yes, it is a fiction in this case about
postponing the, you know, the judgment, as the ox isn't in anguish.
So the other question was, aren't we in some ways using this
situation if we decide we're first going to allow the ox to
be used for a year and then we think we're going to
kill it anyway? So aren't we really extending that?
No, that's true even about a case of a human being. That
until the judgment has been passed, and you didn't even know how
a case is going to be concluded. So the idea of postponing
an execution that you're not allowed to do it and that that
creates anguish is only once the judgment has been passed. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara continues. איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, they raise the
question. Now we already know the answer because of our previous discussion,
but... But let's take a look at this question. יש אומד לנזיקין
או אין אומד לנזיקין. yesh omed lenizikin o ein omed lenizikin. When
damage is caused, do you assess whether it was reasonable for this
damage to have occurred? Meaning, here well here let's spell it out:
מי אמרינן לקטלה הוא דאמדינן בהכי נפקא נשמה ובהכי לא
אמדינן, mi amrinan liktala hu d'amdinan behachi nafka nishama ubehachi lo amdinan,
thank you, בהכי נפקא נפקא בהכי לא נפקא נפקא נשמה. behachi nafka
nafka behachi lo nafka nafka nishama. So we just got through this
whole discussion of באבן או באגרוף, be'even o be'egrof, right? That you
have to basically, the Beit Din has to assess the murder weapon.
And actually it's even more explicit because in the פסוקים psukim in
במדבר, Bamidbar, it says אשר ימות בו הכהו ימות, asher yamut bo
hika'u yamut, right? Anyway it says if he smote him with a
wood weapon that could kill him, then he shall be put to
death. The תורה Torah actually says the weapon has to have the
capacity to kill him. I mean that's like not just a דרש,
drash, that's like פשט pshat in the פסוקים. psukim. Okay, so there
we say that
if I was in a fight with somebody and I hit him
with a stone and, you know, under normal circumstances it wouldn't have
killed him, but in this case it did kill him, I actually
cannot be executed because that was seen like as a freak thing,
it can't be seen as an act of murder. That's what we
say. Now by some כופר? kopher?
Yeah, sort of get off. But I gotta say by the way
that there's a problem there because like what's the scenario about my
intention, right? Like if my intention was just to injure and not
to murder, then even if it could have killed him and he
died, if I genuinely wasn't trying to do that, you know, even
if I was being grossly negligent, I'm still- you still need intention.
You know, here in American law we would call it like manslaughter,
first degree, second degree, if there's gross negligence, but it still wouldn't
be murder. So the only case that you need to have this
rule that the stone had to have and if not he gets
off would be that I was trying to kill him. So get
this case: I'm trying to kill a guy, I take a rock,
I bang it on his head, he dies. Okay, but we say:
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait. That rock really shouldn't have done that
under normal circumstances. You really didn't hit him and you were trying
to kill him, but, you know, you hit him in a place
that shouldn't have killed him. And it happened that it did. So
you're off. You didn't commit murder. Okay, so that's pretty wild, alright?
But that's the הלכה. halacha. That it's not enough that you tried
and that you succeeded. The weapon has to have the ability to
do it, otherwise we say it was a freak thing and you're
off. So the question is, would we say the same by causing
damage? Okay, I take a stone, I, you know, bang- I don't
know- something of Michael's, I bang his, you know, what do I
bang?
I bang your iPhone. Yeah, you like my iPhone example. And it
cracks. And I said, ah, whatever, you know, normally it had a
protective cover on it, it shouldn't have cracked. That was a freak
thing. But I was trying maybe to break it. Okay, but so
do we say well you're off because that was a freak thing?
Okay, now that's again quite funny because we do say אדם מועד
לעולם, adam mu'ad l'olam, right? If you think about that, right? By
damage I don't need intention. Even- I don't even need negligence, right?
If it's me damaging. I mean it's different if it's my ox
or my well or my fire, okay? But maybe the גמרא Gemara
is saying is fine, you didn't need negligence, you didn't need intention,
but it had to have been something that would have normally caused
that damage. And in this case that act shouldn't have normally caused
it. So we'll define that it was a freak thing, it really
wasn't done by that act and therefore you're off. That seems pretty
wild. It's wild enough by murder, but it seems totally wild by
נזק. nezek. Okay, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay. So
מי אמרינן, mi amrinan, do we say לקטלה הוא דאמדינן בהכי נפקא
נשמה ובהכי לא
נפקא נשמה liktala hu d'amdinan behachi nafka nishama ubehachi lo nafka nishama
by murder we say this could have, you know, taken a life
and this could not, and if it doesn't have the ability you
get off,
right,
that we know, right, that we know.
אבל לנזיקין, aval l'nezikin, but for damages, כל דהו? kol d'hu? Now
it doesn't sound like the question is should the law be that
it doesn't matter. It sounds like do we just assume that you
know, many things can cause damage and there's not the same reality
that only certain things have the capacity? Because there's always the capacity
to cause damage. That the גמרא Gemara sounds like it's a factual
question. I would have said it's a legal question: do we care
or not? Or that's one possibility, that by נזק nezek we don't
do אומד, omed, we don't
assess. או דילמא לא שנא, o dilma lo shana, or perhaps it's
no different. תא שמע ta shema come in here. מה בור שיש
בו כדי להמית עשרה טפחים. ma bor sheyesh bo k'dei l'hamit asara
tefachim. So remember we said that if a well is ten טפחים
tefachim deep, then you're liable if an animal dies. Less than ten
טפחים tefachim you're not liable if the animal dies, only if it
gets injured. אף כל שיש בו כדי להמית עשרה טפחים. af kol
sheyesh bo k'dei l'hamit asara tefachim. היו פחות מעשרה טפחים, hayu pachot
me'asara tefachim, it was less than ten טפחים, tefachim, ונפל לתוכו שור
או חמור ומת פטור, v'nafal l'tocho shor o chamor umet patur, and
an ox or donkey falls into it and dies, you're exempt. הוזק
בו, huzak bo, if it's damage, חייב, chayav, you're liable. So מאי
לאו ממטה למעלה קחשיב, mai lav mi'mata l'mala k'chashiv, presumably we're going
from, you know... from like from below to above,
meaning from decreasing in the depth. And what we're saying is the
following: והכי קאמר, v'hachi ka-amar, or excuse me, I read that wrong.
Increasing in the depth. והכי קאמר, v'hachi ka-amar, this is what it's
saying: מטפח ועד עשרה, mi-tefach v'ad asara, from one tefach up to
ten tefachim, מיתה ליכא נזיקין איכא. misa leika nezikin eika. It won't
murder, but it can cause, it won't kill the animal, but it
can cause damage, okay? And therefore you're liable for any damage caused,
meaning ten tefachim you're liable for the death of an animal, anything
less than ten tefachim, anywhere from one to ten, you're liable for
any injury. So if I'm liable for any injury from one to
ten, it means you're not assessing whether this injury was was reasonable
based on this depth. So the Gemara says,
אלמא, alma, you see, לנזיקין כל דהו, l'nezikin kol de-hu, that even
the smallest depth you're liable for damage. שמע מינה אין אומדין, shma
mina ein omdin, you see that you don't assess. The Gemara says
לנזיקין l'nezikin for nezek. The Gemara says לא, lo, no. מלמעלה למטה
קחשיב, mil'maalah l'mata ka-chashiv, we're going from, from a high number to
a low number. והכי קאמר, v'hachi ka-amar, this is how to read
it: עשרה, asara, if it's ten tefachim, מיתה איכא, misa eika, you're
liable for the animal dying. פחות מעשרה, pachus mei-asara, you're less than
ten tefachim, פורתא, purta, a little bit, נזיקין איכא, nezikin eika, so
if it's less than ten, if it's 9.9, then you're liable for
damages. מיתה ליכא, misa leika, not death. Okay? Now 9.9 you're liable
for all damages. But maybe if it's five or three or two
or one, we have to assess whether you're liable or not. ולעולם
אימא לך, u'l'olam eima lach, I would tell you, יש אומד לנזיקין,
yesh omed l'nezikin, everything, you would assess for
nezek, okay? וכל מידי ומידי, v'chol midi u'midi, כהיכי דמזקא ביה, k'heichi
d'mazka bei, בעינן, ba'inan, and for everything we determine, was this well
deep enough to have caused this particular damage? So just because it
says less than ten there's nezek, it doesn't mean that you're always
liable for nezek. Less than ten, you would, you'd be exempt for
death, and for nezek we'd assess case by case. I understand. Okay,
by the way, the other problem with this is that when an
animal dies, it's also nezek. It's not misa. Meaning the Gemara's question
is like is there an issue for murder versus damages, right? So
anyway, it's interesting that it considers that the death of an animal,
you know, is different than the injury of an animal. Anyway, the
Gemara says like this: תא שמע, ta shema, come in here. הכהו
על עינו וסמאה, hikeihu al eino v'sim'ah, if a person hit his
slave, his eved Knaani, on his eye, directly hit his eye and
blinded him, על אזנו וחרשה, al ozno v'cheirshah, on his ear and
made him deaf, so עבד יוצא בהם לחירות, eved yotzei bahem l'cheirus,
he goes free because that's knocking out a limb. By the way,
the ear is interesting because physically the ear is still there, or
the eye, the eye is physically still there, it's just lost its
ability, and we say that that's like, you know, removing it. Okay,
so, so anyway, the Gemara says, that's when the slave goes free.
What does it say in the pasuk about that? It says, it
says,
by hitting it, it says, שישחתנה תחת עינו.
she-yishachatenah tahas eino.
Yeah, but what does it say you did to the eye? What's
the pasuk? כי יכה איש את עין עבדו ושחתה, ki yakeh ish
es ein avdo v'shichatah, it says destroyed it. So destroyed it might
just mean ruined its capacity, its functional capacity, right? So the ear
is an interesting case. Okay, anyway, עבד יוצא בהם לחירות, eved yotzei
bahem l'cheirus, the slave goes free. כנגד עינו ואינו רואה, keneged eino
v'eino ro-eh, opposite the eye, now what Rashi says this means is
like you hit a wall, the guy was standing right here against
the wall, and you went like this, you hit right, and that
somehow, because you hit it right next to his eye, somehow created
some shock and now he can't see. I don't get exactly the
case but that's it, you didn't actually touch him. And now he
can't see. כנגד אזנו ואינו שומע, keneged ozno v'eino shomeia, next to
his ear and he can't hear, אין עבד יוצא בהם לחירות, ein
eved yotzei bahem l'cheirus, he doesn't go free. מאי טעמא, mai ta-ama,
what's the reason? You still caused the injury? לאו משום דבעינן אומדנא,
lav mishum d'ba'inan umdna, it must be because we say no, even
though it looks like you caused the injury, that normally shouldn't have
caused it and you get off because it was this freak thing,
that's why. That it's still like, you know, it's like you caused
the injury but because it was a freak causation you get
off. ושמע מינה יש אומד לנזיקין, u'shma mina yesh omed l'nezikin, you
do assess in cases of
damage. The Gemara says לא, lo, no, משום דאמרינן, mishum d'amrinan, הוא
דאבעית נפשיה, hu d'avise nafshiah, no, that's different, that's because he brought
it upon himself, he scared himself. That, now what does that mean?
It means you shouldn't have caused, your thing didn't really cause it.
Well, isn't that umdna? So it sounds like the Gemara is saying
no, no, no, there's a little bit of a difference. If you
didn't actually touch him, you just did something next to him, that's
not an umdna question. Then that's been clearly assessed like he brought
it upon, you know, he sort of, you didn't injure him, something
you, you know, his reaction to what you did caused this to
happen. So there it's different because you didn't actually touch him. That's
not an umdna question.
That's he brought it upon himself.
So if you're hiding around the corner and you jump out and
you scare someone and they die of a heart attack, you didn't
do anything.
Well, technically you cannot be prosecuted, right.
But I have a better, you know, not better but like you
know, different, like let's say, you know, like I shine like this
really bright light into his eye. Right. I didn't touch him, but
that really could cause blindness. That...
well, that's interesting because... You know, that is a little interesting 'cause
that's like a case about
the difference between shining a light in his
eye and poking and throwing an arrow, so to what degree, right,
is that like a חציב, chatziv, you know, sending because it's not
physical. It's sort of like אש משום חציו, esh mishum chitzo, but
you know, that maybe you are, but that's a little different. That's
something that you projected that directly hit his body.
Fine. So let's say like you know, I think there's between...
although you could say that here also I created sound waves, you
know, by the ears, so maybe.
No, but like, you know, or like we're doing construction, I didn't
warn you, then you're walking then all of a sudden, yes, explode
a building and that caused you to go deaf.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara sounds like. I mean, this is
like all the stuff we had in the first half of בבא
קמא, Bava Kamma, all these formal rules where clearly you caused it,
but technically you're off. Okay, I understand the problem. But the גמרא
Gemara says the problem here is not that it wasn't to be
expected, the problem was that because you didn't do something directly to
him, we define it that he brought it upon himself. I understand
it's bizarre, it doesn't make sense. Yeah, but in that case, you
do presumably, yes. Okay, כדתניא, kidtanya, like we taught in a ברייתא.
Baraisa. המבעית את חבירו פטור מדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמים. Hamavit es
chaveiro patur midinei adam vechayav bidinei shamayim. If you basically scare your
friend, you're exempt, there you go, from judgment down here 'cause technically
you did not do an act of damage. You'll have to pay
up in heaven, which might mean that you have to pay down
here to be exempt up in heaven. כיצד? Keitzad? What's the case?
תקע באזנו
והחרשו Taka be'ozno vechersho פטור. patur. If you basically, like you know,
yelled in his
ear, okay, and you and there you go Michael, and you made
him deaf, you're exempt. אחזו ותקע באזנו והחרשו Achazo vesaka be'ozno vechersho
חייב. chayav. However, if you held on to him while you were
yelling in his ear and you made him go deaf, liable. Because
what's the difference? Okay, presumably the difference is that one case because
you physically make contact with him, it's defined that you did an
act of damage to him. The other case because you didn't make
any physical contact, it's not technically defined as an act of damage.
So I understand that this is very bizarre, but nevertheless the point
is that it's not about that we say it was not normal
for something for this result to have happened. What we say is
technically if you didn't touch him, it's not defined as you did
an act of damage to him. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues.
We still haven't answered the question about יש אומד. yesh omed. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says, תא שמע, ta shma, let's try to
prove it again. חמשה דברים אומדין אותו ונותנין לו מיד. Chamisha devarim
omdin oso venosnin lo miyad.
The five things, right, נזק nezek damage, צער tza'ar pain and suffering,
ריפוי ripui doctor's bill, שבת sheves loss of work, and בשת boshes
embarrassment, you immediately when the damages are occurred, you assess what those
costs are and you pay him. Now that should be obvious. No,
but the point is there are two things, ריפוי ripui and שבת,
sheves, you don't know how long it's going to be the recuperation
period. So normally you would say, give me the receipt at the
end or I'll pay as you go, the hospital bills as they're
coming up, but no, what we do is we assess how much
are we anticipating this, you know, recuperation period is going to take
and how much are the hospital bills and pay it up right
now. And same and and ah, let's take a look. אומדין ונותנין
לו מיד, Omdin venosnin lo miyad, you pay it right away. ריפוי
ושבת עד שיתרפא. Ripui vesheves ad sheyisrapei.
And you pay the ריפוי ripui and שבת, sheves, it doesn't mean
you wait, although it could be read that way, but it doesn't
mean you wait until he gets until he's healed and then you
pay. What it means is you pay now based on how long
it's going to take him to be healed. Okay now, let's say
you're off. אמדו, Amdu, you assessed what that would be, והיה מסתנווה
והולך, vehaya mistanvei veholech, and he was and he was getting worse
and worse, so the recuperation period took longer than expected, אין נותנין
לו
אלא כמו שאמדוהו. ein nosnin lo ela kimo she'amduhu. You don't give
him more, which sounds crazy, right? So maybe it means we made
a bad assessment, maybe it means these things are not fully predictable.
What? I guess that's one way of looking at it, you made
a settlement, but the difference is a settlement is because you chose
to accept that amount, right. Here, you know, you have no choice
in it. So anyway, but what we do is we say, that
was this guy's bad luck, you know, בית דין Beis Din assessed
it really should only take a month and if it took more,
you know, that's your own bad luck. Okay, I don't know what
to say about that. Okay, אמדו והבריא, Amdu vehivri, but the flip
side is let's say he got better in a week and we
thought it was going to take a month, so נותנין לו כל
מה שאמדוהו. nosnin lo kol mah she'amduhu. You pocket the difference because
that was your good luck. The injury so should have caused that
month's worth and it was less, that was your own good luck.
Okay, anyway, שמע מינה shma mina from this we can infer יש
אומד לנזיקין, yesh omed lenizikin, that we assess what it should have
reasonably have cost and if it's more than that, you don't have
to pay more than that. So that sounds like you do an
assessment, right, about what's reasonable. So the גמרא Gemara says no, no,
no, there's a big difference. למימת גברא כמה ליקצר מהא מכה, Limimat
gavra kama liktzar mei'ha maka,
to assess the person how much should he be sick, you know,
as a result of this injury? קצירי Katzirei means sick. פקצירי Fikatzirei
is just the Aramaic word for sick. What can I tell you?
Okay, I understand. No, כמה לא מיקצר, kama lo miktzar, how you
know, how long should he be sick, how long shouldn't. meaning to
assess how much damage was done. My car was in a wreck.
How much is the amount of the damage that was done? So
obviously לא קמיבעי לן lo kamibaya lan and of course that's not
our question. We always assess the damage that was done already. דפשיטא
defshita and we of course we assess it and that's the amount
you have to pay. כי קמיבעי לן ki kamibaya lan that wasn't
our question. Our question was לאומד חפצא le'omed heftza to assess the
object that did the damage. אי עבד האי ניזקא אי לאו i
avad hai nizka i lav whether to assess whether you are liable
for any payment. Do we say that the object that did the
damage really didn't have the capacity and therefore it's a freak thing
and you get off the hook? If you definitely are liable for
damage we're going to do an assessment about what was the cost
of that damage. Okay so we still don't have an answer. Okay
או לא מה o lo ma תא שמע ta shma so finally
we come to the answer that we knew from yesterday. שמעון התימני
אומר Shimon HaTeimani Omer מה אגרוף מיוחד שמסור לעדים Ma egrof meyuchad
shemasur le'eidim אף כל מיוחד שמסור לעדים af kol meyuchad shemasur le'eidim
the same way a fist has to be assessed by the בית
דין Beis Din any item that's
done that's used has to be assessed by the בית דין. Beis
Din. And רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva only disagrees and says it's עדים
eidim it doesn't need the בית דין. Beis Din. But the point
is this פסוק pasuk about a fist or a stone is not
talking about murder. The פסוק pasuk is talking about injury. שמע מינה
shma mina so יש אומד לנזיקין yesh omed lenizikin you see that
even when you're dealing with injury because that's the context of the
פסוק pasuk שמע מינה. shma mina. And that's why we discuss bringing
the ox into בית דין Beis Din according to שמעון התימני. Shimon
HaTeimani. So even for injury you take a stone you bang it
on a guy's car on a guy's window the window you know
and the window shatters and בית דין Beis Din comes and says
well we know you were trying to break the window we know
the window shattered but really it shouldn't have had that effect because
it was a pretty good window and this and that okay you're
off. Right? It seems pretty wild but that's the הלכה. halacha. What?
No. The גמרא Gemara says no no no the only debate of
שמעון התימני Shimon HaTeimani was whether בית דין Beis Din has to
assess it or just the עדים. eidim. But they both agree that
you have to assess the object and that was the context of
the פסוקים psukim was an object of injury not an object of
murder.
Okay everyone agrees and also everyone agrees to
this months-long...
Yeah by the way that's also interesting. We've been learning חובל Chovel
for the last week and a half and this tiny little fact
about how to assess the actual doctor's bills gets stuck in the
middle of this סוגיא. sugya. It's you know it's a little funny
when the גמרא Gemara sort of does it. Okay moving on. אמר
מר amar mar אמדוהו והבריא amduhu vehivri so now we're going to
go back and look at that line. You assessed how much it's
going to cost for doctor bills and he gets better. נותן לו
כל מה שאמדוהו nosen lo kol ma she'amduhu he gets to pocket
the whole thing. It was his good luck that he got better
quickly. מסייע ליה לרבא mesayei lei l'Rava this supports רבא. Rava. דאמר
רבא d'amar Rava רבא Rava says האי מאן דאמדוה לכולי יומא hai
man de'amduhu lekulei yoma ואיטפח לפלגא דיומא ve'itpach lepalga deyoma somebody who
was assessed for a you know that he was going to be
out for the day and he got better in the middle of
the day. כעביד עבידתא ke'avid avidta יהבינן ליה דכולי יומא yahavinan lei
dekulei yoma
and he's able to get up and do his work we still
pay him for being out of work for the whole day the
שבת sheves for the whole day even though he got better in
the middle of the day. Agreed? I guess so. Okay right. דכולי
יומא dekulei yoma משמיא הוא דרחמי עליה mishmaya hu derachamei alei
it was from heaven that he had this good luck but the
actual injury should have caused him to be out for a day.
So it's not like you give your receipts you give your cost
and you get reimbursed. It's like we assess what was the impact
of that injury and anything that happens afterwards is like a change
in that initial reaction. Yes.
So if it's a crime committed and they can't find the weapon
they can't
reimburse?
You mean a crime of murder or
injury.
Right. Well there's difference between injury and murder.
Yes. No both of them need אומד. omed. Both of them you
need the weapon. So that's what the גמרא Gemara concluded for both.
But the answer would be well if the witnesses saw it you
wouldn't have to bring it to court according to שמעון התימני. Shimon
HaTeimani. Yes. If you couldn't bring it to court the guy would
get off.
And if they saw the act but they didn't see
the weapon?
Right so then even according to רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva you would
get off. Even according to רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva you'd get off.
Now the הלכה halacha is that we say that if it's a
metal weapon it doesn't need any assessment and presumably the same would
be true if you're using like a gun. You know? So there
are some cases where we say you don't need to assess no
matter what it was we assume it had that ability. Okay but
in many circumstances the answer would be yes. Yes.
I'm trying to get back to what we just said a second
ago because I just want to make sure I understand this. So
like you know you go to the doctor and the doctor says
well this kind of injury can take a month or it can
take two months.
Who knows which it is? Right. So that's a good question. What
if בית דין Beis Din actually says we can't assess because it's
too indeterminate to assess? Right so that would be a good question.
So I don't know the answer. But you know but maybe you
would say that fine this one will have to wait and see
how it plays out. The גמרא Gemara is assuming that we can
assess and you know and know what it should take. Right. But
you make an excellent point. Like nowadays with our knowledge of medicine
we know there's no way to know what it... and I assume
even then they knew some things take a long time a short
time there's no way to determine it. It's an excellent question. Okay
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. רבא Rava moving on. Moving
on to the next line of the משנה. Mishnah. רקק והגיע בו
הרוק, Rakak vehigi'a bo harok,
if he spat at him and the spit hit him, so then
he pays what was the בושת Boshet damage? 400 זוז zuz or
something, something like that. Yeah, 400 זוז. zuz. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara here makes another interesting point about the same way we had
a discussion of defining an act of נזק, Nezek, like if you
don't touch him it's not an act of נזק, Nezek, an act
of בושת Boshet is also you have to directly encounter the person.
So I can tear off your clothes, right? The woman's head covering,
and that's an act of בושת. Boshet. I didn't touch her body
but I touched her clothes. I can spit at a person, but
we're going to talk about where the spit has to hit. But
if you embarrass somebody without something that's sort of directly engaging the
person's person, you actually are exempt. So let's take a look. I
know, let's take a look. לא שנו אלא בו, Lo shanu ela
bo, it's only if you hit the person directly, it hits him.
אבל בבגדו, Aval bevigdo, but if it only hits his garments, לא,
lo, you don't have to pay בושת. Boshet. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, וניהוי כי ביוש בדברים, Venehei keviyush bidvarim,
why is that any different than if you shame the person with
your words? Right? You let's say you called the person a name
or something, you know, in the middle of
רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, and you mentioned some private thing and you
embarrass somebody publicly in רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim.
So this isn't any worse, so why don't you have to pay?
So אמרי במערבא, Amri b'ma'arava, so they said in מערבא Ma'arava משמיה
דרבי יוסי בר אבין, mishmei deRabbi Yossi bar Avin, זאת אומרת zos
omeres ביוש בדברים biyush bidvarim פטור מכלום. patur miklum.
Yeah, from here you see that if you embarrass somebody just with
your words, there's no payment of the damages. I mean, it's totally
אסור. assur. The גמרא Gemara says like better to be thrown into
a fiery furnace, but it's not considered a tort where there's a
payment of damages. You have to directly do something to the person's
body to be considered that you actually did an act of shaming.
They pay a fine, don't they?
No, that's extremely narrow. That's the one case of the נערה מאורסה.
na'arah me'orasah. Right, generally you don't. So anyway, right, so there's no
so that's so in order the same way to do an act
of נזק, Nezek, we just learned you have to hit the body,
you can't hit near the body, to do an act of בושת,
Boshet, you have to do something to the person's body. Now the
funny thing is, why is tearing off
her head covering or tearing off somebody's clothes, right, the גמרא Gemara
discussed that, why is that an act to their body? You're just
doing it to the clothes. It somehow seems like since it's covering
their body and you're removing what's covering your body, that's sort of
like doing something to their body. But spitting on their clothes isn't
doing it to their body. I don't exactly get the difference. Okay,
but anyway, it's very interesting. In order to be an act of
בושת, Boshet, what is important is, you can pay for just shaming
somebody without
injury. Let's just take a moment to appreciate that. בושת Boshet is
not only in the course of injury. Right, if I just again,
the case of spitting at somebody, pulling off the head covering, I
didn't injure you, I just shamed you, and that is a tort
in itself and you pay purely for an act of shaming. But
it has to be similar to an act of injury, it's something
done to the person's body. Okay, and that's what we're saying here.
You have to have
כוונה kavana להזיק.
lehazik. Yes, בושת Boshet has to have כוונה kavana to either cause
embarrassment or to cause damage. Thank you, that is correct. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara yes.
You know, I'm forgetting the word, but like if people take people
to court if they defame us, say, and
that's what Michael just said, מוציא שם רע. Motzi shem ra. So
right, in American law you can sue somebody for slander. Right, in
הלכה halacha you can't. Again, it's sort of called like גרמא, grama,
any consequential loss of business you have, all of that is considered.
Yeah, there's no real הלכה. halacha. I mean, maybe, you know, גרמי
garmi might cover it, but the basic structure, there's no real compensation
for things like
shaming and slander and all those things. I mean, there's very clear
biblical prohibitions, but that doesn't make it a tort, right? So it's
very interesting. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, איבעיא
להו, Ibayu lehu, so now הכל לפי כבודו. hakol lefi kevodo. Now
if you remember, the משנה Mishnah gave these lists, 200, 400, whatever,
then it says oh, all according to the person's honor. And then
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said everybody has the same honor, everybody is,
you know, descendant of free people, of you know, upper class. So
the גמרא Gemara says איבעיא להו, ibayu lehu, we ask a question,
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma לכולא קאמר או לחומרא קאמר? lekulla k'amar o
lechumra k'amar? When the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma gave numbers and then
said it's based on the person's honor, is he saying based on
the honor you could go down from these numbers, or based on
the honor you would go up from these numbers? Okay, לכולא קאמר,
lekulla k'amar, he's being lenient and saying you would go
down, דאיכא עני de'ika ani דלא בעא למשקל כולי האי delo baye
limshakal kule hai that don't get this amount, the 200, 400, that's
the max. Okay, people that don't have aren't from the upper classes,
they would be less. Okay, או דילמא לחומרא קאמר, o dilma lechumra
k'amar, maybe he's being strict, דאיכא עשיר דבעא לאוסופי ליה טפי. de'ika
ashir d'baye le'osivei lei tfei. No, no,
these are the minimums, based on your honor you would go even
higher than this. So how do you read the תנא קמא? Tanna
Kamma? תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear, מדקאמר רבי עקיבא mideka'amar
Rabbi Akiva אפילו עניים שבישראל afilu aniyim shebeYisrael רואין אותן כאילו הם
בני חורין שירדו מנכסיהם, ro'in osan ke'ilu hem bnei chorin sheyardu minichsehem,
so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, no, even the poor are
deserving as if they are free people who have lost their wealth,
who are sons of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says no, no, even the poor are deserving. So שמע מינה
*shma mina* תנא Tanna, קמא לקולא קאמר *Tanna Kamma lekula ka'amar*. תנא
Tanna, קמא *Tanna Kamma* was saying less and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akivas,
*Rabbi Akiva* says, no, even the poor are deserving of this amount.
שמע מינה *shma mina*. That's a good point. So תנא קמא *Tanna
Kamma* had those numbers as a max and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva:
*Rabbi Akiva* says everybody gets the max. Okay. ומעשה באחד שפרע ראש
האשה *Umaaseh b'echad shepara rosh ha'isha*. He shared this first, he pulled
off this woman's hair covering. ומי יהבינן זמן *U'mi yavinan zman*? And
he said, give me a week, and they gave him a week,
and then during that time he did this trick. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ומי יהבינן זמן *U'mi yavinan zman*? Since when
do we give people time to pay off? I mean assuming they
have the cash available. ואמר רבי חנינא אין נותנין זמן לחבלות *V'amar
Rabbi Chanina ein notnin zman l'chavalos*. You don't give time for paying
off injury, cases of injury. So הכא לא יהבינן זמן *Hacha lo
yavinan zman*. When do we not give people time to pay? לחבלה
*l'chavalah*. If you actually caused a physical injury. דחסריה ממונא *dechashrei mammona*.
You caused actual like loss of value. Okay, you know, you actually
injured my arm or you you know you broke my car. There
was an
actual like loss in my pocketbook. אבל לבושת דלא חסריה ממונא *Aval
l'boshes d'lo chashrei mammona*. In for shame, it might be terrible. Like
you might be much more prepared, you know like if somebody gets
into a car accident you say, is everybody safe? That's the only
thing that matters, right? So you might actually be much more happy
to have your car wrecked than to be publicly shamed. Okay. But
nevertheless, again this just goes to the irony of this, nevertheless since
the money isn't exactly going to replace the lost object, right? It's
not like there's any loss, you know, financial loss. So therefore you
give a person the time to pay it off. It's not like
if that the payment has to immediately rectify the loss. So then
the בושת *boshes* holds when
you're not going to work, I still have to pay the שבת
*sheves* right away, right?
Yeah, that's probably true. That's probably true. Okay, now שמר ועמדה על
פתח חצר *Shamar v'amda al pesach chatzer*. He watched till she was
there by the opening of her courtyard, presumably by the main street,
he spilled the oil, the whole thing. והתניא *V'hatanya*. And רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* said, look, you're not even you're not allowed
to injure yourself, but if you do you're exempt. If somebody else
injures you, they have to pay. So okay, that was his response.
והתניא *V'hatanya*. But we taught in a ברייתא Braita: *Beraisa*. אמר לו
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Amar lo Rabbi Akiva*. Rabbi Akiva said to
him. This is the great phrase: צללת במים אדירים והעלית חרס בידך
*Tzalalta b'mayim adirim v'haalisa cheres b'yadecha*. You dived into clear waters...
oh that's a good point, you're right, I didn't trip think that.
You dived into clear waters, okay, or to mighty waters, and you
came up with a piece of pottery. Like thinking about the person
that's going deep sea diving for like these sunken treasures, you deep
sea dive into this whatever and you came up with garbage. Okay,
you did this whole big thing and you got nothing out of
it. אדם רשאי לחבל בעצמו *Adam rashai l'chavel b'atzmo*. A person's allowed
to injure themselves. Now that's different than the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. The
משנה *Mishnah* said you're not allowed to injure yourself, but there's no
payment. Okay, he is saying a person can injure themselves if they
want. Big deal that she did it to herself. So how do
you deal with this? Is a person allowed to injure themselves or
not? This is a very generally leads to a very important
question, right? Plastic... oh right, are you allowed even if you just
do it for fun? You know, I don't know, fun, there's some
people that have a psychological thing they cut they have to cut
themselves, you know. Are you allowed, is there a problem with causing
self-injury? So אמר רבא לא קשיא כאן בחבלה כאן בבושת *Amar Rava
lo kashya kan b'chavalah kan b'voshes*.
There's a difference between physical injury, actually physically wounding yourself, which you're
not allowed, as opposed to embarrassing yourself that you are allowed if
you want to. So that's why when he says you're not allowed,
he means you're not allowed to wound yourself. In this ברייתא Braita
*Beraisa* where he says you're allowed to, he means you're allowed to
embarrass yourself. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, wait a minute, והמתניתין
בבושת היא *v'hamatnisin b'voshes hi*?
But our משנה *Mishnah* was talking about shaming. דקתני החובל בעצמו אף
על פי שאינו רשאי פטור *deketani hachovel b'atzmo af al pi she'eino
rashai pator*. That's where רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says you're not allowed
to injure yourself. So clearly it means you're not even allowed to
embarrass yourself. No, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, הכי קאמר ליה
*Hachi ka'amar lei*. This is what he said to him. לא מבעיא
בושת *Lo mibaya boshes*. It goes without saying that when it comes
to embarrassment דאדם רשאי לבייש את עצמו *d'adam rashai l'vayeish es atzmo*.
You are allowed to embarrass yourself, like רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* said
in the ברייתא Braita, *Beraisa*. אלא ela, אפילו חבלה chabala *Ella afilu
chavalah*. But even when it comes to personal injury דאין אדם רשאי
לחבל בעצמו *d'ein adam rashai l'chavel b'atzmo*. You're not allowed to wound
yourself. Nevertheless, אחרים שחבלו בו חייבין *acherim shechavlu bo chayavin*.
People that do cause wounding, they do have to pay. So in
this case she could embarrass herself if she wants. But even if
it was a wounding, people are not allowed to wound themselves, but
there won't be a consequence. Doesn't mean that you're that if you
wound them you don't have to pay.
Okay, so the beginning part when he says צללת במים אדירים *Tzalalta
b'mayim adirim*... yeah. And it says אדם רשאי לחבל בעצמו *Adam rashai
l'chavel b'atzmo*
he means לבייש עצמו *l'vayeish atzmo*. So now we're reconciling it by
saying you're allowed to embarrass yourself but you're not allowed to wound
yourself, but either way when you did, that's what they're doing to
themselves, when you did it you have to pay. But now we're
going to focus on this question: Are you allowed to wound yourself?
The way we've reconciled this, both of these משנה *Mishnah* and ברייתא
Braita. *Beraisa* says you're not allowed to wound yourself, maybe you're allowed
to embarrass yourself. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says: Is this
really true? ואין אדם רשאי לחבול בעצמו? Ve'ein adam rashai lachavol be'atzmo?
Is a person not allowed to wound themselves? והא תניא, Vehata tanya,
we taught in a ברייתא: Braita יכול נשבע להרע לעצמו ולא הרע
יפטר? Yachol nishba le'hara le'atzmo velo hara ye'patter? If somebody takes an
oath to do injury to themselves—so if you take an oath of
something that is not binding, let's say you take an oath to
violate a מצוה, mitzvah, something you're not allowed to do, okay, so
then if you don't keep by the oath, you're exempt because the
oath was never binding in the first place. So let's say you
take an oath to do injury to yourself. Should we say that
the oath is not binding and therefore if you violate it, you're
exempt? So that's what this asks. And it says, the ברייתא Braita
says: You maybe you think the oath would not be binding and
you would be exempt because you took an oath to injure yourself,
maybe that's not a valid oath. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse
teaches: להרע או להיטיב. Le'hara o lehiteev. You took an oath to
do evil or to do good. מה הטבה רשות אף הרעה רשות.
Mah hatava reshus, af hara reshus. The same way you have the
permission to do good to yourself or to others, so whatever you
have the permission to do injury to yourself and therefore because we're
not learning שבועות Shevuos we're not going to discuss that. We're going
to focus on the point for us. Okay? So you have permission
to do injury to yourself, so such an oath is binding even
if it's an oath to do injury to yourself. So הוי נשבע
להרע בעצמו ולא הרע. avi nishba le'hara be'atzmo velo hara. So that
includes somebody—it doesn't work if you take an oath to do injury
to another person. You're not allowed to injure another person. So that's
the point of this ברייתא, Braita the rest of this ברייתא. Braita
An oath to do injury to another person is not binding, but
an oath to do injury to yourself, you're allowed to do injury
to self, so it is binding. So this ברייתא Braita makes it
very clear: you're allowed to injure yourself. Okay, so doesn't that say
you are allowed to injure yourself? אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, so שמואל
Shmuel says: ביושב בתענית. Be'yoshev be'ta'anis. No, no, no, we don't mean
physical wounding. We mean doing bad to yourself. So you can make
an oath to be in a fast, to sit a day fast.
That's hurting yourself and you're not eating. That you're allowed to do
but you're not allowed to do injury to yourself. So the גמרא
Gemara says: One minute. That doesn't sit with the parallel because it
says it works about yourself, it doesn't work about others. דחבישתא גבי
הרעתו אחרים להושיבם בתענית? Dehuvsa gabei haraso acherim lehoshivam be'ta'anis? So what
does it mean? Oh, but it doesn't work if you take an
oath to do bad to other people. So what would that mean
now? It doesn't work if you take an oath to make other
people sit a fast day? Like what's the case that you could
do something like that? How do I make you sit a fast
day? אחרים מי מצית להושיב להו בתעניתא? Achrim mi matzi lehoseiv lehu
be'ta'anisa? How could you ever do that? What would that even be
to make somebody keep a fast day? So the גמרא Gemara says:
Yes, you could do it! You know how I'll make you keep
a fast day? In forced starvation! דמהדק להו באנדרונא. Demadeik lehu be'androna.
I lock you in a room. Sure you could do that. I
can enforce starvation on somebody. Okay, so that's the case. We're talking
about starving yourself or starving other people. That you are allowed to
starve yourself—I mean not to the point that would cause permanent injury
but for a period of time. That's not real injury. Our issue
is causing real injury. Okay, והא תניא, vehatanya, one minute, you can't
say that because the ברייתא Braita: clarifies what type of injury we're
talking about. איזו היא הרעת אחרים? Eizu hi harat acherim? What is
the type of injury to others that the oath is not binding?
אכה פלוני, Ekeh ploni, I'm going to hit so and so, ואפצע
מוחו, ve'eftza mocho, and I'll smash in his head, his skull. Okay,
that's pretty graphic. That's a little more than injury. That's like murder.
So אלא, so it's clear that this ברייתא says you're—if you take
an oath about yourself it is binding because you are allowed to
do that to yourself. So there's no way out of it. This
ברייתא is clear: you're allowed to cause real injury to yourself. So
the גמרא Gemara says: Fine, אלא תנאי היא. ela tanna'i hi. It's
a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. דאיכא מאן דאמר רשאי לחבול בעצמו, De'ika
man de'amar reshai lachavol be'atzmo, some say a person is allowed to
cause injury to themselves, and some say that a person is not.
Okay, and by the way, as תוספות Tosafos points out, that might
have been the two רבי עקיבא, not the way we reconciled it
before. That might have been two versions of רבי עקיבא: one has
him say you're allowed to injure yourself, and one has him say
you're not allowed to injure yourself. Because there's actually a debate of
תנאים, Tannaim, are you allowed—I
mean תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי עקיבא. Trei Tannai leiba de'Rabbi Akiva. Yeah.
Yeah, that's what תוספות—anyway. Tosafos So there might actually be—but there is
a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. There's no question that the רבי עקיבא
of our משנה says you're not allowed to injure yourself. And this
ברייתא says you're allowed to take an oath to injure yourself, you
are allowed to injure yourself. So now the גמרא Gemara says: מאן
תנא דשמעתיה דאמר אין אדם רשאי לחבול בעצמו? Man tanna deshamishei de'amar
ein adam rashai lachavol be'atzmo? Who is the תנא, I mean other
than רבי עקיבא, but like where do we see this idea sort
of expounded upon and maybe you could also say what's the basis
for this idea that a person is not allowed to cause physical
injury to themselves? דהאי תנא הוא, De'hai tanna hu, the following תנא,
דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: ואך את דמכם לנפשותיכם אדרוש.
Ve'ach es dimchem lenafshoseichem edrosh. Your blood for your souls I will
seek out.
What does this mean? רבי אלעזר אומר: Rabbi Elazar Omer: מיד נפשותיכם
אדרוש את דמכם. Miyad nafshoseichem edrosh es dimchem. I will punish your
souls for the spilling of your blood, meaning for committing suicide. This
is a verse that prohibits the committing of suicide. Ah, so you
see, that's the basis that you're not allowed to injure yourself. So
the גמרא Gemara says: Wait, wait, there's a little bit of a
difference between suicide and injury. So the גמרא says: One minute. דילמא
קטלא שאני. Dilma ketala shani. I'd like to think that everybody would
agree that you're not allowed to commit suicide. Okay, that's actual murder
and so on. But maybe injury—and now you could also discuss different
degrees of injury. Is it an injury that heals or an injury
that doesn't heal? Like when we say there's a person that says
you're allowed to injure yourself, do we really think there's somebody that
says I'm allowed to cut off my arm if I want to
cut off my arm? Or do we think it means I can
make like a cut in myself that'll take time to heal. Okay,
so clearly there are different degrees. Hopefully nobody disagrees about the suicide.
That's a different question. אלא האי תנא הוא דתניא, Ela hai tanna
hu detanya, the following tanna, תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: מקרעין על המת
ולא מדרכי האמורי. Mekare'in al hamet velo midarchei ha'emori. You can tear
up garments—not the one garment that you're wearing—you can destroy objects, tear
them up over grief over a dead body, and that's not seen
as pagan practices. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, Rabbi Elazar says:
שמעתי שמקרע על המת יותר
מדאי לוקה משום בל תשחית. Shamati shemekare'a al hamet yoter midai loke
mishum bal tashchit.
You get lashes because of the prohibition of, as it says by
the fruit-bearing tree when you're going to lay siege, do not destroy
the tree. So that for him is abstracted to mean don't do
any type of wasteful destruction. Okay, now how is that relevant? Well,
יתר מדאי. yoter midai. No, first of all you have to do
it a little bit.
Right. But then there's stuff that's seen as excessive. That's always the
question: what's considered wasteful? Right? You know, it's like, I don't know,
if some people pay two thousand dollars to go to see Hamilton
or something, that's, you could say that's בל תשחית, bal tashchit, right?
I mean, what's wasteful? How much of excessive is considered to
be appropriate use for the thing. Anyway, so the גמרא says,
so anyway, so you see according to him, there's a concept of
בל תשחית, bal tashchit, right, that is more abstracted. So if it
applies to property, it should apply to your
body, וכל שכן גופו, vechol sheken gufo, certainly it should apply to
your body. So the גמרא says: no. ודילמא בגדים שאני. U'dilma begadim
shani. No, actually בל תשחית bal tashchit could apply to clothes and
not to your body. How's that true? Why? כי פסידא דלא הדרא
הוא.
Ki
pesida delo hadra hu.
Clothes don't get better. Now, for this means everybody would agree murder
is, I mean suicide is אסור, assur, thank God. Everybody would also
agree cutting off a finger, doing some type of permanent injury to
yourself is forbidden, at least on the basis of בל תשחית. bal
tashchit. The question is, injuring yourself in a non-permanent way. You know,
and there are some people that they'll beat themselves up, not just
figuratively, literally, they'll actually inflict injury, the body will heal, it won't
be permanent, so it's not בל תשחית. bal tashchit. Is that allowed?
Okay, כי הא דרבי יוחנן, Ki ha deRabbi Yochanan, like Rabbi Yochanan,
קרי למאניה מכבדותא. kari lemanei mechabduta. He calls his clothes the things
that give honor to me, which means that he took care of
his clothing and he recognized that you wear clothing, it gives honor
to the body. רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, and רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
כד הוה מסגי ביני היזמי והיגי, kad hava masgi beinei hizmei vehigi,
when he was walking amongst thorns and thistles, מדלי להו למאניה, madlei
lehu lemanei, he would lift up his cloak and he'd get his
ankles all scraped. He'd rather get his ankles scraped than get his
clothes torn. אמר זה מעלה ארוכה וזה אינו מעלה ארוכה, Amar ze
ma'ale arucha veze eino ma'ale arucha, the scrapes and the on my
ankles and on my shins, they'll get a scab, they'll heal, but
my clothes don't work that way. If my clothes are torn, they
won't heal. Okay, so yes, there could be a בל תשחית bal
tashchit on objects, and if you're not doing permanent damage to yourself,
it's not בל תשחית. bal tashchit. So are you allowed to do
self-injury if it is non-permanent and it's not בל תשחית? bal tashchit?
אלא האי תנא הוא, Ela hai tanna hu, and if so, what
would it be based on? It's the following tanna, דתניא, detanya, we
taught in a Braita, אמר רבי אלעזר הקפר ברבי: Amar Rabbi Elazar
HaKappar beRabbi: מה תלמוד לומר וכפר עליו מאשר חטא על הנפש? ma
talmud lomar vekipper alav measher chata al hanefesh? A נזיר Nazir will
bring a קרבן korban and atone for himself because he sinned against
the soul. Now the simple sentence is talking about a נזיר Nazir
who is טמא, tamei, and נפש nefesh here means because he came
in contact with a dead body. But we read it more generally.
וכי באיזה נפש חטא זה? Vechi be'eizeh nefesh chata ze?
Against which soul did a נזיר Nazir sin? אלא שציער עצמו מן
היין. Ela shetzi'er atzmo min hayayin. We're back to the tanna,
he withheld from himself wine, he withheld this pleasure. Okay, והלא דברים
קל וחומר, vehalo devarim kal vachomer,
and it's a קל וחומר: kal vachomer: ומה זה שלא ציער עצמו
אלא מן היין נקרא חוטא, u'mah ze shelo tzi'er atzmo ela min
hayayin nikra chotei, if just withholding from yourself the pleasure of wine
you're called a sinner, המצער עצמו מכל דבר על אחת כמה וכמה,
hametza'er atzmo mikol davar al achat kama vechama, how much more so
if you withhold, if you cause affliction to yourself based on anything.
So now that's a pretty weak basis for the prohibition of injury.
Number one, it's not even a verse, it's not even a prohibition,
it's נקרא חוטא. nikra chotei. And then it has nothing to do
with injury, like then it would be like if I forego a
nice dessert, I'm a sinner. And is there any qualitative difference... I
love hearing that! Okay, right. Is there any qualitative difference
between causing some type of any type of affliction, like sitting in
a תענית, ta'anit, accepting an unnecessary תענית? ta'anit? Right, I want to
see if I can do a little thing of testing my endurance
and I'm going to skip lunch today. Okay, so it doesn't sound
like the issue of causing physical injury is the same question as
this. So it's interesting that רמב"ם, Rambam, when he speaks about the
prohibition to do injury to yourself, רמב"ם Rambam says a person is
prohibited to be
חובל, chovel, which means literally wound, חבלה specifically. Means that blood comes
as a result, so רמב"ם Rambam says a person is prohibited to
wound another person and even himself he's prohibited to wound. And then
the רמב"ם Rambam says and not only that, a person can't even
smite another person and it transgresses a biblical prohibition because it says
לא יוסף להכותו. Lo yosif lehakoto. You might know right when you
give lashes it says you can't give them excessive, so we say
from that well if this guy doing the מצווה Mitzvah of בית
דין Beis Din can't give lashes, this applies to anybody that you
cannot hit somebody else. But the question is fine, hitting even without
causing a wound, that you can't do to somebody else that's a
biblical prohibition. But when the רמב"ם Rambam said you can't wound yourself,
is that based on this פסוק Pasuk of לא יוסף להכותו? Lo
yosif lehakoto? What's it based on? Okay, so it's very interesting. The
גמרא has this idea of a prohibition to wound, but it's very
unclear whether it's just this amorphous idea of you're not supposed to
hurt yourself וכולי, v'chulu, it really includes a wide range of things.
From the רמב"ם Rambam it sounds a little bit like he's trying
to get it into the prohibition of hitting someone, but that's generally
understood to mean hitting someone else. So it remains pretty unclear what
the basis for this is.
But what if you're not but you know I'm going to hurt
myself now I'm going to look more beautiful, plastic surgery, right?
Yeah, that's a different question. That's not considered wounding. Michael raises the
important question like when is wounding considered wounding? When you go into
surgery that's not wounding, that's helping, right? So yes, and רב משה
Rav Moshe has a whole תשובה Teshuvah about plastic surgery and so
on.
And there are the five categories.